A Finding Aid to the James Vigeveno Galleries Records, 1940-1975, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
James Vigeveno Galleries records
1940-1975
Archives of American Art
James Vigeveno Galleries
AAA.jamevige
Archival Resource Key
2.9 Linear feet
The records of California gallery James Vigeveno Galleries measure 2.9 linear feet and date from 1940 to 1975. The collection comprises sales records consisting of photograph albums, negatives, and card files; printed materials containing exhibition announcements and catalogs, and scrapbooks documenting exhibitions held at the gallery; and two photographic portraits of Vigeveno.
Biographical / Historical
The James Vigeveno Galleries operated in Los Angeles from 1940 to 1956 and Ojai, a music and art/craft community located just north of Los Angeles, from 1957 to 1975. From 1957 to 1964 there were also periodic exhibitions of works from the Vigeveno Collection at the Bel-Air Hotel. Vigeveno (1895-1977) dealt primarily with French "modern and primitive" works, including artists of the School of Paris. American art, especially artists from California, were also represented. In addition, Chinese ceramics and Dutch and Flemish old master paintings were exhibited. Artists represented included Grandma Moses, Everett Shinn, John O'Shea, Rouault, Picasso, Chagall, Utrillo, William Ritschell, and others.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as three series.
Series 1: Sales Records, 1941-1981 (2.0 linear feet; Boxes 1-2, 4)
Series 2: Printed Materials, 1941-1981 (0.8 linear feet; Boxes 2-3, 5)
Series 3: Portraits of Vigeveno, 1941-1981 (2 folders; Boxes 3, 5)
Scope and Contents
The records of California gallery James Vigeveno Galleries measure 2.9 linear feet and date from 1940 to 1975. The collection comprises sales records consisting of photograph albums, negatives, and card files; printed materials containing exhibition announcements and catalogs, and scrapbooks documenting exhibitions held at the gallery; and two photographic portraits of Vigeveno.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The James Vigeveno Galleries photograph albums were donated in 1987 by Annie Vigeveno, James Vigeveno's widow. Other material was donated in 2001, 2002, and 2005 by Tim and Lynn Mason, collectors of California art.
Scrapbooks; Art galleries, Commercial -- California; Vigeveno, James, d. 1977
- Sales Records, circa 1950-1975; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 2 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, 4
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains 41 photograph albums of paintings sold through the gallery, accompanied by a full content list of artist names along with the titles of artwork in chronological order. Also included are slides, transparencies, and 169 negatives of the French and European modernist paintings that were sold by the Vigeveno Galleries during its years of operation. These negatives are accompanied by a full list of artwork and artist names in alphabetical order.
  Other sales records consist of two sets of index cards. The first set is arranged by artist name along with names of galleries or collectors. The second set is arranged by gallery or collector name along with the name of the artwork sold. None of the records in the series note any pricing information.
  Arrangement
  The photographs were removed from the albums in which they were received for preservation purposes, but the original order of the photographs has been retained.
  - Card File by Artist Name, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Card File by Gallery/Collector Name, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photograph Albums, Full Content List, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photograph Albums, Books 1-32, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2-33)
  - Photograph Albums, Books 33-41, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-9)
  - Negatives, Full List of Artwork, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Negatives, Beauchant-Buffet, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Negatives, Chagall-Clave, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Negatives, Degas-Jawlensky, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Negatives, Kisling-Moore, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Negatives, Picasso-Rouault, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Negatives, Segonzac-Utrillo, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Negatives, Valtat-Vuillard, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Slides and Transparencies, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Printed Materials, 1940-1964; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 2-3, 5
  Series consists of a complete set of chronologically arranged announcements and catalogs for exhibitions held at the James Vigeveno Galleries, and three scrapbooks containing clippings of articles about exhibitions held from 1940 to 1956. The series also includes a chronological list of the gallery's exhibitions.
  - Chronological List of Exhibitions, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1940-1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1956-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1961-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Ojai, California Location, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Bel-Air Hotel Location, 1957-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook for Exhibitions 1-39, 1940-1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook for Exhibitions 40-108, 1944-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook for Exhibitions 109-154, 1950-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Portraits of Vigeveno, circa 1956; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Boxes 3, 5
  Series consists of two photographic portraits of the gallery owner, James Vigeveno.
  - Photograph of Vigeveno, 1940-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photograph of Vigeveno, circa 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)